Guide to the Henry Hale Bucher, Jr. Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Henry Hale Bucher, Jr. Papers
1936-2013
RG 250
Yale University Divinity School Library
4.5
(9 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, and collected material document the life and work of Henry Hale Bucher, Jr., focusing on his participation in ecumenical study and mission abroad programs, his work with the University Christian Movement and other organizations concerning Middle East and Jewish-Christian issues, and his draft resistance during the Vietnam war.
Bucher, Henry Hale, 1936-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Henry Hale Bucher, Jr., 2012-2014
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Biographical / Historical
Chronology
1936 March 7 Born in Hainan, China, son of Presbyterian missionaries Henry Hale Bucher, Sr. and Louise Scott Bucher
1937 Sep Bucher family moved to Hong Kong, staying at Phillips House, due to health reasons and Sino-Japanese war.
1938 Family returned to Hainan, stationed in Nodoa.
1939 Conditions on Hainan deteriorating due to Japanese occupation, the family left for furlough in the U.S. Christmas 1939 was spent in Roanoke, Virginia.
1940 Sep Family returned to China.
1941 Jan Bucher family evacuated to Philippine Islands, initially staying in Baguio and later Manila.
1941 Dec Family evacuated to Los Baños during bombing of Manila, then returned to Manila.
1944 Jul Family relocated from occupied Manila to Los Baños internment camp. Food became scarce as internment continued.
1945 Feb U.S. soldiers and Filipinos enabled the escape of internees from Los Baños camp; internees housed on New Bilibad prison grounds until repatriation.
1945 May Bucher family returned to U.S. on USS Eberlee and went to New Jersey and later to Hartford, Connecticut
1946 Dec Family returned to China, stationed at Kiungchow [now Qiongshan], Hainan
1948-1949 Henry, Jr. and his older sister Anna attended boarding school at Shanghai American School. In spring 1949, with General Mao's advancing forces, Henry and sister were evacuated on the USS Repose.
1949 Jul Bucher family returned to U.S. and resided in New Jersey.
1954 Graduated from high school in New Jersey and entered Davidson College
1956-1957 Participated in Junior Year Abroad program sponsored by Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A., attending American University of Beirut in Lebanon.
1958 Decided to complete studies at American University of Beirut, graduated with B.A.
1960-1961 While attending Princeton Theological Seminary, participated in Seminary Year Abroad program at University of Ghana, Legon
1962 Received M.Div. from Princeton Theological Seminary
1962-1965 Served as Frontier Intern in Mission under World Student Christian Federation and Presbyterian Church, U.S.A., and Paris Mission Society, stationed in France and Gabon
1965-1969 Served on staff of Department of Higher Education, National Council of Churches, and Field Director, University Christian Movement
1967-1968 HHB, Jr. and more than 900 others who had draft status exempting them from draft for Vietnam War, sent their draft cards to Yale University Chaplain William Sloane Coffin, who handed them in to the Justice Department in protest of the War. In response, the Selective Service System reclassified them as I-A, making them vulnerable to the draft, and many law suits followed, including "Bucher (et.al) vs. Selective Service System." The government lost this case, setting a new legal precedent that draft reclassification could not be used as "punishment" for free speech.
1971 M.A. from University of Wisconsin-Madison in Comparative World History
1971-1973 Ford Fellow, University Wisconsin-Madison
1973-1974 Fulbright/Hays Doctoral Dissertation Research Abroad Fellow to France, Gabon, and Senegal
1977 Ph.D. in Comparative World History, University of Wisconsin-Madison. Dissertation: "The Mpongwe of the Gabon estuary: a history to 1860"
1977-1980 Academic staff, International Studies and Programs, University of Wisconsin-Madison
1980-1985 Educational Consultant with GLOBE (Global Learning Opportunities in Basic Education) and pastor in Bryn Mawr Presbyterian Church in Cottage Grove, Wisconsin
2004- Chaplain Emeritus and Adjunct Associate Professor / Humanities, Austin College, Sherman, Texas
1985-2004 Chaplain and Associate Professor of Humanities at Austin College, Sherman, TX
Scope and Contents
The correspondence, writings, and collected material in the papers of Henry Hale Bucher, Jr. are focused on specific areas that are complementary to other collections at the Yale, including his participation in ecumenical study abroad programs, his work with the University Christian Movement, and his draft resistance in a movement that involved Yale Chaplain William Sloane Coffin. This collection should be examined in connection with the papers of Henry Hale Bucher, Jr.'s parents, the Henry Hale Bucher and Louise Scott Bucher Papers in Yale Divinity Library Record Group No. 249. Henry, Jr.'s early life is well documented in the papers of his parents.
This collection provides personal papers that complement organizational archives held at Yale, including the archives of the World Student Christian Federation (YDSL Record Group No. 46) and the University Christian Movement Archives (YDSL Record Group No. 235), and the papers of William Sloane Coffin (Manuscripts and Archives, MS 1665) and Margaret Flory (YDSL Record Group No. 86).
The Family Correspondence of Series I dates from 1955 to 1968 and primarily documents Henry, Jr.'s participation in a Junior Year Abroad program at the American University of Beirut, a Seminary Year Abroad program at the University of Ghana, Legon, his work as a Frontier Intern in Mission in France and Gabon, his work with university students when based in New York, and his Vietnam War draft resistance. The General Correspondence of Series II covers the same general time period. There is a focus within it on Bucher's interest in mission history in Africa and efforts to gather documentation. Correspondence specifically related to his study programs and work is in Series III.
Series III, Activities Documentation, is a chronological gathering of correspondence and collected materials from the various eras of Bucher's life from his Junior Year Abroad in college to his involvement in Vietnam War-era draft resistance. Areas of particular interest are Bucher's documentation of the 1964 coup that occurred in Gabon when he was there as a Frontier Intern in Mission, his ongoing interest in issues related to the Middle East, and many clippings, articles, and court documents related to his draft resistance. More information about the draft resistance effort is available in a book documenting the Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam organization: "Because of their Faith: CALCAV and Religious Opposition to the Vietnam War by Mitchell K. Hall (New York: Columbia University Press, 1990).
Series IV, Writings, includes published and unpublished writings of Bucher, sermons, and journals.
Series V, Personal Items and Memorabilia, contains biographical documentation, photographs, audio material, and artifacts that generally correspond to the areas of Bucher's life documented in the earlier series. A button and pin collection of more than 480 items provides a valuable window on social and political issues in America since the 1960s, including civil rights, the Vietnam war, drug culture, peacemaking, and ecology.
Arrangement
I. Family Correspondence
II. General Correspondence
III. Activities Documentation
IV. Writings
V. Personal Items and Memorabilia
Church work with students; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Draft resisters.; Bucher, Henry Hale, 1936-; Frontier Internship in Mission Programme
- Family Correspondence, 1955-1997; Series I
  - Letters to parents
    - From World Council of Churches work camp in Finland, and traveling in Israel and Africa, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - From American University of Beirut and traveling in Israel, Turkey, Europe, 1958 Apr-Aug (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Primarily from Princeton Theological Seminary, 1958 Oct - 1959 Mar (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - From Nigeria and Ghana, 1960 Sep-Nov (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - From France and Switzerland, 1963 Feb-May (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - From Gabon, 1964 Mar - 1965 Apr (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - From New York and elsewhere in U.S., 1965 Jul - 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters to/from extended family
    - To/from Aunt Clara Scott, 1956-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - From Uncle Bob and Aunt Carol Bucher, missionaries in Iran, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - To/from Aunt Hettie and Uncle Frank Davey, 1948-1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - To/from other family members including sister Anna, sister Priscilla, brother Scott, 1956-1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Postcards to sister Priscilla
    - Primarily from Lebanon, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Primarily from Princeton Theological Seminary, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Primarily postcards made from photographs, sent by HHB, Jr. in Africa, 1960-1961, 1964, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- General Correspondence, 1958-1995; Series II
  - Including from Yupa Oonyawongse in Thailand, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - To/from Ray Teeuwisen, fraternal worker in Cameroon, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - HHB, Jr. letter to Albert Schweitzer and reply written by nurse, with signed note by Schweitzer, 1963 Apr, Jun (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Primarily regarding efforts to gather historical documentation on history of missions in Gabon and Robert Hamill Nassau, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - From Andrew F. Walls regarding Society for African Church History, 1964 Jun (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Primarily regarding documentation of Protestantism in Gabon, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - To/from First Presbyterian Church, Haddonfield, New Jersey, re. HHB, Jr. stance on Vietnam war, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Primarily to/from colleagues related to Africa, 1967-1980, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Activities Documentation, 1956-1970; Series III
  - Junior Year Abroad: Lebanon
    - "Junior Year Abroad Letters" from HHB, Jr. at American University of Beirut (mimeographed circular letters), 1956 Nov - 1957 Jun (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Follow-up correspondence with colleagues and acquaintances in program, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Seminary Year Abroad: Ghana
    - "Seminary Year Abroad Letters" from HHB, Jr. at University College, Legon, Ghana, 1960 Oct - 1961 Jun (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Clipping showing American and African students at University College of Ghana; "Open Letter to All African Governments from African Students in Russia", ca. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Frontier Internship in Mission: Paris, Gabon
    - "Frontier Internship in Mission Letters" from HHB, Jr. in Paris and Gabon (mimeographed circular letters), 1962 Dec - 1963 Dec (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Report letters from HHB, Jr. to FIM program leadership, Margaret Flory of Presbyterian Church, U.S.A. and Erica Brucker of Paris Mission Society, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Three year report: "Evaluation of Frontier Intern Study and Service Project: Gabon" by HHB, Jr., 1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Administrative correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Program material and notes, 1962-1963, no date (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Collected material regarding 1964 coup in Gabon, including student response (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Collected material regarding 1964 coup in Gabon (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - HHB, Jr. description of and reaction to Gabon coup: "Summary of Political Events in Libreville, February 18-20, 1964" (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - HHB, Jr. description of and reaction to Gabon coup: report letters addressed to Phil Bosserman, Director of Peace Corps in Gabon, 1964 Mar (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - HHB, Jr. description of and reaction to Gabon coup: report letters addressed to Phil Bosserman, 1964 Apr (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - HHB, Jr. description of and reaction to Gabon coup: report letters addressed to Phil Bosserman, 1964 May, Dec (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Map, article re. Gabon; metal franc, money of Baraka Protestant Mission, 1968, no date (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence with other Frontier Interns and regarding program, 1962-1964, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Related to Middle East
    Scope and Contents
    Materials in this section date from HHB, Jr.'s work on the staff of the University Christian Movement (1964-1969) and Americans for Middle East Understanding (1969), as member of National Council of Churches Mid-East Panel, and in later years.
    - Correspondence
      - Including letters to editors, to Norton Mezvinsky, American Council for Judaism, 1967 Jan - 1968 Feb (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Including with American Council for Judaism, 1968 Mar-Apr (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Including re. WSCF Beirut consultation, with Humphrey Walz, 1968 May-Jul (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Including regarding National Jewish Community Relations Advisory Council conference on Anti-Semitism and American Council for Judaism, 1968 Aug-Dec (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Including with Humphrey Walz and American Jewish Committee, 1969 Jan-Feb (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Including regarding packet on Middle East sent out by University Christian Movement, 1969 Mar-Oct (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Including regarding Middle East Peace Project, Madison Campus Ministry, 1975-1994, no date (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Collected material
      - Related to National Council of Churches Middle East Panel, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - University Christian Movement Middle East packet, Resolution on the Middle East, statements regarding UCM goals and perspectives; clipping re. disbanding of UCM, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Publications of American Council for Judaism, 1967-1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Related to Norton Mezvinsky and Michael Selzer, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Newsclippings, press releases, notes, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Related to Vietnam War
    - Correspondence
      - To/from family members, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - To/from family members, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - To/from Stephen Allen, Leonard Boudin, Homer Bradshaw (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - To/from First Presbyterian Church of Haddonfield, NJ, Robert Gladden, Appeal Agent, Local Board No. 7 for New Jersey, 1967-1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - To/from Morris Karpatkin, Dean Kelley, Senator Robert F. Kennedy, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - To/from Law Center for Constitutional Rights, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - To/from Raymond Morris, President Richard Nixon, West Jersey Presbytery and others, 1967-1969, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Court documents
      - Henry Hale Bucher, Jr. vs. Selective Service System, Local Board No. 7: Civil Action Verified Complaint:, 1967 Nov (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Henry Hale Bucher, Jr. vs. Selective Service System, Local Board No. 7: Plaintiff's Memorandum, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Bucher et al vs. Selective Service System: Amended Complaint, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Bucher et al vs. Selective Service System: Second Amended Complaint, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Bucher et al vs. Selective Service System: Brief for Appellants, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Bucher et al vs. Selective Service System: Opinion of Court, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Bucher et al vs. Selective Service System: summary of case from Westlaw.com (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Statements/notes
      - Statement by William Sloane Coffin when HHB, Jr. draft card handed in; Selective Service history for HHB, Jr.; Statement of HHB, Jr. concerning the turning in of his draft card, 1967 Oct-Nov (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Statement prepared for Local Board No. 7; Statement by HHB, Jr. after being reclassified by Local Board 7, 1967 Dec (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Notes from diary; prepared packet of documents, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Collected material
      - National Council of Churches resolutions, documents, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Press release from American Civil Liberties Union, 1967 Dec (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Documents from Central Committee for Conscientious Objectors, Clergy and Laymen Concerned About Vietnam, "Resist" bulletin, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Documents from Commission on Youth Service Project, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Miscellaneous memos and documents about Vietnam War draft resistance, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Newspaper and magazine clippings re. Bucher case and Vietnam War, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Newspaper and magazine clippings re. Bucher case and Vietnam War, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Writings, 1957-2013; Series IV
  - Student papers
    - "John Leighton Wilson: Robert Hamill Nassau - Gabon's Response to Christian Missions: 1842-1890, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - "The Gabon Evangelical Church: A Response to Christian Missions - 1890-1961"; paper re. doctrinal changes in West Africa, 1970, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Journals
    - Notebook describing travels on return from seminary abroad year, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Notebook describing trip back to birthplace in China, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Typescript papers, essays
    - "Ecumenical Work Camps - Evaluation: Aspo, Finland"; writings from period at American University of Beirut, ca. 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Writings related to Gabon coup, 1964, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - "Christianity Looks at Zionism" - ACJ 25th Anniversary Conference, 1968 Oct (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Athens and Jerusalem - A Theology for the Crisis in the Middle East: February, 1969", 1969 Feb (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sermons, notes
    - Typescript sermons and talks, 1962-1970, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Handwritten notes, primarily for talks, 1958, 1968-1969, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Handwritten notes, primarily for talks (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Published writings
    - Book: The Third World: The Middle East (Dushkin Publishing Group, 1984) (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Article: "Radical Obedience" in New, the Media Album, Vol. 3: No. 3, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Article: "John Leighton Wilson and the Mpongwe" in Journal of Presbyterian History; "Apartheid and Slavery: Some Parallels in Christianity and Crisis, 1976, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Articles: "Third World Sermon Notes"; "Warning: Investing Yourself May Change You, Your World View, and Your Future" in Transitions Abroad, 1979-2004 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Edited work: "Two Women" by Robert Hamill Nassau, with Isabella Ann Nassau, digitized by Henry Hale Bucher, Jr. from the 1911 typescript with expanded notes and commentary, 2011 (in book format and files on CD and flash drive), 2013 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous brief writings, 1967-1984 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1936-2012; Series V
  - Biographical documentation
    - Childhood, including at Shanghai American School, China, 1936-1949 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Youth, in New Jersey, 1950-1954 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - At Davidson College, Junior Year Abroad at American University of Beirut, 1955-1958 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - At University of Ghana, Princeton Theological Seminary, ordination, Frontier Intern in Mission, draft cards, 1960-1968 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - At University of Wisconsin, consultant at GLOBE, chaplain at Austin College, 1972-1999 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - "China Memoirs" from 2002 reunion of Shanghai American School; certificate from Manila Liberation Reunion; Junior Year Abroad 50th anniversary survey (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - "Where in the World was Henry Bucher" (booklet prepared by Austin College alumni association), 2012 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photographs
    - Childhood and youth, 1940s-1955 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Primarily Junior year abroad - Beirut, 1956-1958 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Primarily Princeton Theological Seminary and seminary year abroad in Ghana, 1959-1962 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Primarily from FIM period in Gabon, including with Albert Schweitzer, 1962-1965 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - HHB, Jr. and family photos, 1967-1970s (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - HHB, Jr. and family, including trip to China and Thailand, 1990s-2008 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Audio
    - Related to Middle East, including by Benjamin and Carol Weir, Christy Wilson, Rabbi Marc Tannenbaum (5 cassettes), 1968-1986 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - HHB, Jr. interviews with Alice Osuka, Gabon (audiocassette and CD), 1964 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Artifacts
    - Hat worn by HHB, Jr. at AFSC-sponsored international work camp in Evan Saphir, Israel, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Copies of framed plaques, one signed by Albert Schweitzer, 1976, 2003, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Button (Pin) collection
    More than 480 buttons and pins collected by Henry Hale Bucher, Jr. provide a window on social and political issues in America since the 1960s, including civil rights, the Vietnam war, drug culture, peacemaking, and ecology. A full listing of the buttons is available in Box OV-1 and at http://divinity-adhoc.library.yale.edu/Resources/Bucher_Buttons.pdf.
    - Vietnam war, 1960s-1970s (Box OV1)
    - Civil Rights, 1960s-1980s (Box OV1)
    - Civil Rights / Women's Rights, 1960s-1970s (Box OV2)
    - Drug subculture, 1960s (Box OV2)
    - Peace / Peacemaking, 1960s-1980s (Box OV2)
    - God / Planet / Ecology, 1960s-1980s (Box OV3)
    - Political, 1960s-1970s (Box OV3)
    - Middle East / Africa / Southern Americas / China, 1960s-2000s (Box OV3)